<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-jones-ace-cwt-proof-of-possession-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Proof-of-Possession Key for CWTs">Proof-of-Possession Key Semantics for CBOR Web Tokens (CWTs)</title>

    <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
        <uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="April" year="2017"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>ACE Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>CBOR Web Token</keyword>
    <keyword>CWT</keyword>
    <keyword>Proof-of-Possession</keyword>
    <keyword>Holder-of-Key</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This specification describes how to declare in a CBOR Web Token (CWT)
	that the presenter of the CWT possesses a particular proof-of-possession key
	and how the recipient can cryptographically confirm
	proof of possession of the key by the presenter.
	Being able to prove possession of a key is also sometimes described as
	the presenter being a holder-of-key.
	This specification is a profile of "Proof-of-Possession Key Semantics for JSON Web Tokens (JWTs)" (RFC 7800),
	but using CBOR and CWTs rather than JSON and JWTs.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="Introduction">
      <t>
        This specification describes how a CBOR Web Token <xref target="CWT"/> can declare
	that the presenter of the CWT possesses a particular proof-of-possession (PoP) key
	and how the recipient can cryptographically confirm
	proof of possession of the key by the presenter.
	Proof of possession of a key is also sometimes described as
	the presenter being a holder-of-key.
	This specification is a profile of "Proof-of-Possession Key Semantics for JSON Web Tokens (JWTs)" <xref target="RFC7800"/>,
	but using CBOR <xref target="RFC7049"/> and CWTs <xref target="CWT"/>
	rather than JSON <xref target="RFC7159"/> and JWTs <xref target="JWT"/>.
     </t>

     <section title="Notational Conventions" anchor="NotationalConventions">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
       and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Unless otherwise noted, all the protocol parameter names and values are case sensitive.
       </t>
     </section>
    </section>

    <section title='Terminology' anchor='Terminology'>
      <t>
	This specification uses terms defined in
	the CBOR Web Token <xref target="CWT"/>,
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-cose-msg"/>, and
	Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR) <xref target="RFC7049"/>
	specifications.
      </t>

      <t>
	These terms are defined by this specification:
      </t>

      <t>
	<list style="hanging">

	  <t hangText="Issuer">
	    <vspace/>
	    Party that creates the CWT and binds the proof-of-possession key to it.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="Presenter">
	    <vspace/>
	    Party that proves possession of a private key (for asymmetric key cryptography)
	    or secret key (for symmetric key cryptography) to a recipient.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="Recipient">
	    <vspace/>
	    Party that receives the CWT containing the proof-of-possession key information from the presenter.
	  </t>

	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Representations for Proof-of-Possession Keys' anchor="PoP">
      <t>
	By including a <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> (confirmation) claim in a CWT,
	the issuer of the CWT declares that the presenter possesses a particular key
	and that the recipient can cryptographically confirm that
	the presenter has possession of that key.
	The value of the <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> claim is a JSON object
	and the members of that object identify the proof-of-possession key.
      </t>
      <t>
	The presenter can be identified in one of several ways by the CWT
	depending upon the application requirements.
	If the CWT contains a <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx> (subject) claim <xref target="CWT"/>,
	the presenter is normally the subject identified by the CWT.
	(In some applications, the subject identifier will be relative to
	the issuer identified by the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> (issuer) claim <xref target="CWT"/>.)
	If the CWT contains no <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx> claim,
	the presenter is normally the issuer identified by the CWT
	using the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> claim.
	The case in which the presenter is the subject of the CWT is analogous to
	Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) 2.0 <xref target="OASIS.saml-core-2.0-os"/> SubjectConfirmation usage.
	At least one of the <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx>
	claims MUST be present in the CWT.
	Some use cases may require that both be present.
      </t>

      <section title="Confirmation Claim" anchor="Confirmation">
	<t>
	  The <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> claim is used in the CWT
	  to contain members used to identify the proof-of-possession key.
	  Other members of the <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> object may be defined because
	  a proof-of-possession key may not be the only means of confirming
	  the authenticity of the token.
	  This is analogous to the SAML 2.0 <xref target="OASIS.saml-core-2.0-os"/>
	  SubjectConfirmation element in which a number of different
	  subject confirmation methods can be included
	  (including proof-of-possession key information).
	</t>
	<t>
	  The set of confirmation members that a
	  CWT must contain to be considered valid is context dependent
	  and is outside the scope of this specification.
	  Specific applications of CWTs will require implementations
	  to understand and process some confirmation members in particular ways.
	  However, in the absence of such requirements, all confirmation members
	  that are not understood by implementations MUST be ignored.
	</t>
	<t>
	  This specification establishes the
	  IANA "CWT Confirmation Methods" registry for these members
	  in <xref target="CnfReg"/> and registers the members defined by this specification.
	  Other specifications can register
	  other members used for confirmation, including other members for
	  conveying proof-of-possession keys using different key
	  representations.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> claim value MUST represent only a single
	  proof-of-possession key; thus, at most one of the
	  <spanx style="verb">COSE_Key</spanx>
	  and <spanx style="verb">Encrypted_COSE_Key</spanx>
	  <!-- and <spanx style="verb">jku</spanx> (JWK Set URL) -->
	  confirmation values defined below may be present.
	  Note that if an application needs to represent multiple proof-of-possession
	  keys in the same CWT, one way for it to achieve this is to
	  use other claim names, in addition to <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx>,
	  to hold the additional proof-of-possession key information.
	  These claims could use the same syntax and semantics
	  as the <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> claim.
	  Those claims would be defined by applications or other specifications
	  and could be registered in
	  the IANA "CBOR Web Token Claims" registry <xref target="IANA.CWT.Claims"/>.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Representation of an Asymmetric Proof-of-Possession Key" anchor="PrivatePoP">

	<t>
	  When the key held by the presenter is an asymmetric private key,
	  the <spanx style="verb">COSE_Key</spanx> member
	  is a COSE_Key <xref target="I-D.ietf-cose-msg"/>
	  representing the corresponding asymmetric public key.
	  The following example demonstrates such a declaration
	  in the CWT Claims Set of a CWT:
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  {
   "iss": "https://server.example.com",
   "aud": "https://client.example.org",
   "exp": 1361398824,
   "cnf":{
     "COSE_Key":{
       "kty": "EC",
       "crv": "P-256",
       "x": "18wHLeIgW9wVN6VD1Txgpqy2LszYkMf6J8njVAibvhM",
       "y": "-V4dS4UaLMgP_4fY4j8ir7cl1TXlFdAgcx55o7TkcSA"
      }
    }
  }
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>
	  The COSE_Key MUST contain the required key members for a COSE_Key of that key type
	  and MAY contain other COSE_Key members,
	  including the <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx> (Key ID) member.
	</t>

	<t>
	  The <spanx style="verb">COSE_Key</spanx> member MAY also be used for a COSE_Key
	  representing a symmetric key, provided that the CWT is encrypted
	  so that the key is not revealed to unintended parties.
	  The means of encrypting a CWT is explained in <xref target="CWT"/>.
	  If the CWT is not encrypted, the symmetric key MUST be encrypted as described below.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Representation of an Encrypted Symmetric Proof-of-Possession Key" anchor="SymmetricPoP">

	<t>
	  When the key held by the presenter is a symmetric key,
	  the <spanx style="verb">Encrypted_COSE_Key</spanx> member
	  is an encrypted COSE_Key <xref target="I-D.ietf-cose-msg"/>
	  representing the symmetric key
	  encrypted to a key known to the recipient
	  using COSE_Encrypt or COSE_Encrypt0.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The following example illustrates a symmetric key that could subsequently be
	  encrypted for use in the <spanx style="verb">Encrypted_COSE_Key</spanx> member:
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  {
   "kty": "oct",
   "alg": "HS256",
   "k": "ZoRSOrFzN_FzUA5XKMYoVHyzff5oRJxl-IXRtztJ6uE"
  }
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
	  The COSE_Key representation
	  is used as the plaintext when encrypting the key.
	  The COSE_Key could, for instance, be encrypted using a COSE_Encrypt0 representation
	  using the AES-CCM-16-64-128 algorithm.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The following example CWT Claims Set of a CWT illustrates
	  the use of an encrypted symmetric key as the
	  <spanx style="verb">Encrypted_COSE_Key</spanx> member value:
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  {
   "iss": "https://server.example.com",
   "sub": "24400320",
   "aud": "s6BhdRkqt3",
   "exp": 1311281970,
   "iat": 1311280970,
   "cnf":{
     "Encrypted_COSE_Key":
       "(TBD)"
     }
  }
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Representation of a Key ID for a Proof-of-Possession Key" anchor="KidPoP">

	<t>
	  The proof-of-possession key can also be identified by the use of
	  a Key ID instead of communicating the actual key,
	  provided the recipient is able to obtain the identified key
	  using the Key ID.
	  In this case,
	  the issuer of a CWT declares that the presenter possesses a particular key
	  and that the recipient can cryptographically confirm
	  proof of possession of the key by the presenter by including a
	  <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> claim in the CWT
	  whose value is a JSON object with the JSON object containing a
	  <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx> member
	  identifying the key.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The following example demonstrates such a declaration
	  in the CWT Claims Set of a CWT:
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  {
   "iss": "https://server.example.com",
   "aud": "https://client.example.org",
   "exp": 1361398824,
   "cnf":{
     "kid": "dfd1aa97-6d8d-4575-a0fe-34b96de2bfad"
    }
  }
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
	  The content of the <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx> value is application specific.
	  For instance, some applications may choose to use a cryptographic hash of the public key
	  value as the <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx> value.
	</t>
      </section>

<!--
      <section title="Representation of a URL for a Proof-of-Possession Key" anchor="jkuPoP">

	<t>
	  The proof-of-possession key can be passed by reference
	  instead of being passed by value.
	  This is done using the <spanx style="verb">jku</spanx> member.
	  Its value is a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/> that refers to a
	  resource for a set of JSON-encoded public keys represented as a JWK Set <xref target="JWK" />,
	  one of which is the proof-of-possession key.
	  If there are multiple keys in the referenced JWK Set document,
	  a <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx> member MUST also be included
	  with the referenced key's JWK also containing the same <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx> value.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The protocol used to acquire the resource MUST provide
	  integrity protection.  An HTTP GET request to retrieve the
	  JWK Set MUST use TLS
	  <xref target="RFC5246"/> and
	  the identity of the server MUST be validated, as per
	  Section 6 of <xref target="RFC6125">RFC 6125</xref>.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The following example demonstrates such a declaration
	  in the CWT Claims Set of a CWT:
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  {
   "iss": "https://server.example.com",
   "sub": "17760704",
   "aud": "https://client.example.org",
   "exp": 1440804813,
   "cnf":{
     "jku": "https://keys.example.net/pop-keys.json",
     "kid": "2015-08-28"
    }
  }
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
      </section>
-->

      <section title="Specifics Intentionally Not Specified" anchor="NotSpecified">
	<t>
	  Proof of possession is typically demonstrated by having the presenter sign
	  a value determined by the recipient using the key possessed by the presenter.
	  This value is sometimes called a "nonce" or a "challenge".
	</t>
	<t>
	  The means of communicating the nonce and the nature of its contents
	  are intentionally not described in this specification,
	  as different protocols will communicate this information in different ways.
	  Likewise, the means of communicating the signed nonce is also not specified,
	  as this is also protocol specific.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Note that another means of proving possession of the key
	  when it is a symmetric key is to encrypt the key to the recipient.
	  The means of obtaining a key for the recipient is likewise protocol specific.
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        All of the security considerations that
        are discussed in <xref target="CWT"/> also apply here.
        In addition, proof of possession introduces its own unique security issues.
	Possessing a key is only valuable if it is kept secret.
	Appropriate means must be used to ensure that unintended parties
	do not learn private key or symmetric key values.
      </t>
      <t>
	Applications utilizing proof of possession should also utilize audience restriction,
	as described in Section 4.1.3 of <xref target="JWT"/>,
	as it provides different protections.
	Proof of possession can be used by recipients to reject messages from unauthorized senders.
	Audience restriction can be used by recipients to reject messages intended for different recipients.
      </t>
      <t>
	A recipient might not understand the <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> claim.
	Applications that require
	the proof-of-possession keys communicated with it
	to be understood and processed must ensure that
	the parts of this specification that they use are implemented.
      </t>
      <t>
	Proof of possession via encrypted symmetric secrets is subject to replay attacks.
	This attack can, for example, be avoided when a signed nonce or challenge is used
	since the recipient can use a distinct nonce or challenge for each interaction.
	Replay can also be avoided if a sub-key is derived from a shared secret
	that is specific to the instance of the PoP demonstration.
      </t>
      <t>
	As is the case with other information included in a CWT,
	it is necessary to apply data origin authentication and integrity protection
	(via a keyed message digest or a digital signature).
	Data origin authentication ensures that the recipient of the CWT
	learns about the entity that created the CWT
	since this will be important for any policy decisions.
	Integrity protection prevents an adversary from changing
	any elements conveyed within the CWT payload.
	Special care has to be applied when carrying symmetric keys inside the CWT
	since those not only require integrity protection
	but also confidentiality protection.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>
	A proof-of-possession key can be used as a correlation handle if the same key
	is used with multiple parties.
	Thus, for privacy reasons, it is recommended that different proof-of-possession keys
	be used when interacting with different parties.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
	The following registration procedure is used for all the
	registries established by this specification.
      </t>
      <t>
	Values are registered on a Specification Required
	<xref target="RFC5226"/> basis after a three-week review period on the cwt-reg-review@ietf.org mailing
	list, on the advice of one or more Designated Experts. However, to allow for the
	allocation of values prior to publication, the Designated Experts may approve
	registration once they are satisfied that such a specification will be published.
	[[ Note to the RFC Editor:
	The name of the mailing list should be determined in consultation
	with the IESG and IANA. Suggested name: cwt-reg-review@ietf.org. ]]
       </t>
      <t>
	Registration requests sent to the mailing list for review should use
	an appropriate subject
	(e.g., "Request to Register CWT Confirmation Method: example").
	Registration requests that are undetermined for
	a period longer than 21 days can be brought to the IESG's attention
	(using the iesg@ietf.org mailing list) for resolution.
      </t>
      <t>
	Criteria that should be applied by the Designated Experts include
	determining whether the proposed registration duplicates existing functionality,
	determining whether it is likely to be of general applicability
	or whether it is useful only for a single application, and
	evaluating the security properties of the item being registered
	and whether the registration makes sense.
      </t>
      <t>
	It is suggested that multiple Designated Experts be appointed who are able to
	represent the perspectives of different applications using this specification
	in order to enable broadly informed review of registration decisions.
	In cases where a registration decision could be perceived as
	creating a conflict of interest for a particular Expert,
	that Expert should defer to the judgment of the other Experts.
      </t>

      <section anchor="ClaimsRegistry" title="CBOR Web Token Claims Registration">
	<t>
	  This specification registers the  <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> claim in the IANA
	  "CBOR Web Token Claims" registry <xref target="IANA.CWT.Claims"/>
	  established by <xref target="CWT"/>.
	</t>

	<section anchor='ClaimsContents' title='Registry Contents'>
	  <t>
	    <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
	    <list style='symbols'>
	      <t>
		Claim Name: <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Claim Description: Confirmation
	      </t>
	      <t>JWT Claim Name: <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx></t>
	      <t>CBOR Key Value: TBD (maybe 8)</t>
	      <t>CBOR Major Type: 5</t>
	      <t>
		Change Controller: IESG
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Specification Document(s): <xref target="Confirmation"/> of [[ this document ]]
	      </t>
	    </list>
	  </t>
	</section>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
      </section>

      <section title="CWT Confirmation Methods Registry" anchor="CnfReg">
	<t>
	  This specification establishes the
	  IANA "CWT Confirmation Methods" registry
	  for CWT <spanx style="verb">cnf</spanx> member values.
	  The registry records the confirmation method member
	  and a reference to the specification that defines it.
	</t>

        <section title="Registration Template" anchor="CnfTemplate">
          <t>
            <list style='hanging'>
              <t hangText='Confirmation Method Name:'>
                <vspace/>
                The human-readable name requested (e.g., "kid").
              </t>
              <t hangText='Confirmation Method Description:'>
                <vspace/>
                Brief description of the confirmation method (e.g., "Key Identifier").
              </t>
	      <t hangText='JWT Conformation Method Name:'>
		<vspace/>
		Claim Name of the equivalent JWT confirmation method value,
		as registered in <xref target="IANA.JWT.Claims"/>.
		CWT claims should normally have a corresponding JWT claim.
		If a corresponding JWT claim would not make sense,
		the Designated Experts can choose to accept registrations
		for which the JWT Claim Name is listed as "N/A".
	      </t>
	      <t hangText='CBOR Key Value:'>
		<vspace/>
		Key value for the confirmation method.
		The key value MUST be an integer in the range of 1 to 65536.
	      </t>
	      <t hangText='CBOR Major Type:'>
		<vspace/>
		CBOR major type and, when applicable, minor type for the claim.
	      </t>
              <t hangText='Change Controller:'>
                <vspace/>
                For Standards Track RFCs, list the "IESG". For others, give the name of the
                responsible party. Other details (e.g., postal address, email address, home page
                URI) may also be included.
              </t>
              <t hangText='Specification Document(s):'>
                <vspace/>
                Reference to the document or documents that specify the parameter,
		preferably including URIs that
                can be used to retrieve copies of the documents.
		An indication of the relevant
                sections may also be included but is not required.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Initial Registry Contents" anchor="CnfContents">
          <t> <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">COSE_Key</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Description: COSE_Key Representing Public Key
              </t>
	      <t>
		JWT Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">jwk</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Key Value: 1
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Major Type: 5
	      </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="PrivatePoP"/> of [[ this document ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">Encrypted_COSE_Key</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Description: Encrypted COSE_Key
              </t>
	      <t>
		JWT Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">jwe</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Key Value: 2
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Major Type: 4 (with an optional 6 tag prefix)
	      </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="SymmetricPoP"/> of [[ this document ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Description: Key Identifier
              </t>
	      <t>
		JWT Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Key Value: 3
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Major Type: 2
	      </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="KidPoP"/> of [[ this document ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
<!--
          <t>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">jku</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Confirmation Method Description: JWK Set URL
              </t>
	      <t>
		JWT Confirmation Method Name: <spanx style="verb">jku</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Key Value: TBD
	      </t>
	      <t>
		CBOR Major Type: 3
	      </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="jkuPoP"/> of [[ this document ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
-->
	</section>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
      </section>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6125.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7049.xml' ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-cose-msg-24"?>

      <reference anchor="CWT" target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-ace-cbor-web-token-04">
	<front>
	  <title abbrev="CBOR Web Token">CBOR Web Token (CWT)</title>

	  <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
	    <organization>Microsoft</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
	      <uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
	    </address>
	  </author>

	  <author initials="E." surname="Wahlström" fullname="Erik Wahlström">
	    <organization></organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>erik@wahlstromstekniska.se</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="Samuel Erdtman" initials="S.E." surname="Erdtman">
	    <organization>Spotify AB</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>erdtman@spotify.com</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig">
	    <organization>ARM Ltd.</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@arm.com</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>

	  <date day="13" month="April" year="2017" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in Progress," value="draft-ietf-ace-cbor-web-token-04"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IANA.CWT.Claims" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/cwt">
        <front>
          <title>CBOR Web Token Claims</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
	  <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7159.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7800.xml' ?>

      <reference anchor="JWT" target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7519'>
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Token (JWT)</title>
	  <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
	    <organization>Microsoft</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
	      <uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
	    <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>ve7jtb@ve7jtb.com</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
	    <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>n-sakimura@nri.co.jp</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <date month="May" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7519"/>
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7159"/>
      </reference>

      <!-- <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml2/reference.OASIS.saml-core-2.0-os.xml' ?> -->

      <reference anchor="OASIS.saml-core-2.0-os" target="http://docs.oasis-open.org/security/saml/v2.0/">
	<front>
	  <title>Assertions and Protocol for the OASIS Security Assertion Markup Language
	  (SAML) V2.0</title>
	  <author fullname="Scott Cantor" initials="S." surname="Cantor">
            <organization>Internet2</organization>
            <address>
	      <email>cantor.2@osu.edu</email>
            </address>
	  </author>
	  <author fullname="John Kemp" initials="J." surname="Kemp">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
            <address>
	      <email>John.Kemp@nokia.com</email>
            </address>
	  </author>
	  <author fullname="Rob Philpott" initials="R." surname="Philpott">
            <organization>RSA Security</organization>
            <address>
	      <email>rphilpott@rsasecurity.com</email>
            </address>
	  </author>
	  <author fullname="Eve Maler" initials="E." surname="Maler">
            <organization>Sun Microsystems</organization>
            <address>
	      <email>eve.maler@sun.com</email>
            </address>
	  </author>
	  <date year="2005" month="March"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="OASIS Standard" value="saml-core-2.0-os"/>
	<format type="PDF" target="http://docs.oasis-open.org/security/saml/v2.0/saml-core-2.0-os.pdf"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IANA.JWT.Claims" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/jwt">
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Token Claims</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
	  <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section title='Acknowledgements' anchor='Acknowledgements' numbered="no">
      <t>
	TBD
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="TBD" title="Open Issues">
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
	    Convert the examples from JSON/JWT to CBOR/CWT.
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Document History" anchor="History">
      <t>
	[[ to be removed by the RFC Editor before publication as an RFC ]]
      </t>

      <t>
        -00
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
            Created the initial draft from RFC 7800.
	  </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>     

  </back>
</rfc>
